<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Himanshu Dave</title>
    <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://davehimanshu.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Himanshu Dave</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Himanshu Dave</title>
      <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms of drag reduction by semi-dilute inertial particles in a turulent channel flow</title>
      <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/publication/channel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davehimanshu.github.io/publication/channel/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The volume-filtering immersed boundary method</title>
      <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/publication/vfib/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davehimanshu.github.io/publication/vfib/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modulation of turbulent structures using inertial particles to achieve drag reduction</title>
      <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/research_projects/dr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davehimanshu.github.io/research_projects/dr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A vast majority of woth worlds energy resources (Crude oil and natural gas) are transported through pipelines spanning thousands of miles. Pumping fluids through these pipelines for thousands of miles proves to be a significant challenge requiring pumping stations every 50 miles on average. Advances in efficient fluid transport can bring a transformative impact in the Petroleum and natural gas industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The largest inefficiency within pipelines arises from pressure-losses stemming from the shear stress produced at the walls acting on the fluid. In this project we show that inertial particles introduced within a turbulent channel flow even at semi-dilute volume fractions can significant alter the skin-friction drag at the walls by modifying the coherent flow structures.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-paticle-laden-turbulent-channel-flow-at-mathrmre_tau--180-showing-contours-of-particle-volume-fraction-majority-of-the-particles-reside-in-low-speed-regions-of-the-flow&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A paticle-laden turbulent channel flow at $\mathrm{Re}_\tau = 180$ showing contours of particle volume fraction. Majority of the particles reside in low-speed regions of the flow.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/dr_1_hu4c7e212139982341074274fc317a6d5d_214670_f1eb078c1bc431e5c3f6dba2b0e4a7f2.webp 400w,
               /media/dr_1_hu4c7e212139982341074274fc317a6d5d_214670_2d1a0347515fae14c3baf5252a13e862.webp 760w,
               /media/dr_1_hu4c7e212139982341074274fc317a6d5d_214670_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/dr_1_hu4c7e212139982341074274fc317a6d5d_214670_f1eb078c1bc431e5c3f6dba2b0e4a7f2.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;286&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure&amp;nbsp;&#34; data-post=&#34;:&amp;nbsp;&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
      A paticle-laden turbulent channel flow at $\mathrm{Re}_\tau = 180$ showing contours of particle volume fraction. Majority of the particles reside in low-speed regions of the flow.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A two-way modulation is observed that is based on particle inertia. Low inertial particles at ($\mathrm{St}^+ = 6$) actually produce a drag increase and reduce the mass flow rate whereas high inertial particles ($\mathrm{St}^+ = 30$) produce drag reduction and increase the mass flow rate. The magnitude of change observed is amplified as the mass loading is increased.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-visually-looking-at-the-flow-shows-an-increase-in-mass-flow-rate-compared-to-the-particle-free-channel-flow-with-laden-with-higher-inertial-particles-lower-inertial-particles-tend-the-reduce-the-mass-flow-rate-compared-to-the-particle-free-channel-flow&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Visually looking at the flow shows an increase in mass flow rate compared to the particle-free channel flow with laden with higher inertial particles. Lower inertial particles tend the reduce the mass flow rate compared to the particle-free channel flow&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/dr_2_hu2ea053faa90ad995409e11e2550c5d1a_88417_212a9d6f4666d98ab62a8209a96e1152.webp 400w,
               /media/dr_2_hu2ea053faa90ad995409e11e2550c5d1a_88417_e26fcb4ad1ef2bbc4a85c711360c2931.webp 760w,
               /media/dr_2_hu2ea053faa90ad995409e11e2550c5d1a_88417_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/dr_2_hu2ea053faa90ad995409e11e2550c5d1a_88417_212a9d6f4666d98ab62a8209a96e1152.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;505&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure&amp;nbsp;&#34; data-post=&#34;:&amp;nbsp;&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
      Visually looking at the flow shows an increase in mass flow rate compared to the particle-free channel flow with laden with higher inertial particles. Lower inertial particles tend the reduce the mass flow rate compared to the particle-free channel flow
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;



















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-average-streamwise-velocity-as-a-function-of-the-wall-normal-distance-for-a-mathrmst--6-and-b-mathrmst--30-at-various-mass-loadings-the-solid-black-line-represents-the-particle-free-channel-darker-symbols-correspond-to-larger-mass-loadings-which-vary-from-02-10&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Average streamwise velocity as a function of the wall normal distance for (a) $\mathrm{St}^&amp;#43; = 6$ and (b) $\mathrm{St}^&amp;#43; = 30$ at various mass loadings. The solid black line represents the particle-free channel. Darker symbols correspond to larger mass loadings which vary from 0.2-1.0.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/dr_3_hub8a63c9c37b655f296429afd54e969a3_80616_9df69aedc9d211b6456c50595eaaef2f.webp 400w,
               /media/dr_3_hub8a63c9c37b655f296429afd54e969a3_80616_51fe395385e41d49a99788de83b786d7.webp 760w,
               /media/dr_3_hub8a63c9c37b655f296429afd54e969a3_80616_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/dr_3_hub8a63c9c37b655f296429afd54e969a3_80616_9df69aedc9d211b6456c50595eaaef2f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;286&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure&amp;nbsp;&#34; data-post=&#34;:&amp;nbsp;&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
      Average streamwise velocity as a function of the wall normal distance for (a) $\mathrm{St}^+ = 6$ and (b) $\mathrm{St}^+ = 30$ at various mass loadings. The solid black line represents the particle-free channel. Darker symbols correspond to larger mass loadings which vary from 0.2-1.0.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particles modulate the flow structures due to two underlying mechanisms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preferential concentration&lt;/strong&gt;: The migration of inertial particles from vortical regions to straining regions of the flow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turbophoresis&lt;/strong&gt;: The migration of inertial particles to lower turbulence regions near the walls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present research we witness a major distinction between how lower inertial particles segregate themselves within the flow compared to higher inertial particles and how that affects if drag is reduced or augmented. This strongly affects how the low-speed regions of flow are observed. Higher inertial particles which produce a reduction in drag (i.e. increase in mass flow rate) tend to form long ropes near the wall with a relative volume fraction of $\phi/\phi_0 = 3$ or higher. These long ropes reside in the low-speed regions of the flow and help increase the spacing between them in the spanwise direction. This tends to increase the mass flow rate by reducing the number of bursting events from coherent structures. The ropes tend to make the coherent structures more stable around them, overall reducing the amount of wall-shear stress produced.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-the-formation-of-stable-particles-ropes-help-keep-the-coherent-structures-quasi-streamwise-vortices-around-them-stable-for-long-periods-of-time-the-pink-contour-shows-the-particle-ropes-existing-between-two-counter-rotating-vortices&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The formation of stable particles ropes help keep the coherent structures (quasi-streamwise vortices) around them stable for long periods of time. The pink contour shows the particle ropes existing between two counter-rotating vortices.&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/dr_4_hu6aa276f30b7908604a771c3069bdba35_736365_91db9a32d1129fc4c60d4dd9ee6e9ff0.webp 400w,
               /media/dr_4_hu6aa276f30b7908604a771c3069bdba35_736365_abfb358ed20e2b41b128d840bd7eb6f5.webp 760w,
               /media/dr_4_hu6aa276f30b7908604a771c3069bdba35_736365_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/dr_4_hu6aa276f30b7908604a771c3069bdba35_736365_91db9a32d1129fc4c60d4dd9ee6e9ff0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;455&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure&amp;nbsp;&#34; data-post=&#34;:&amp;nbsp;&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
      The formation of stable particles ropes help keep the coherent structures (quasi-streamwise vortices) around them stable for long periods of time. The pink contour shows the particle ropes existing between two counter-rotating vortices.
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A remarkable obersvation is how these ropes tend to remain stable for long periods of time. In comparison lower inertial particles are more spread apart into smaller clusters and dont show the same characteristics as higher inertial particles, hence producing an increase in drag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top-down view of pseudocolor of Particle volume fraction near the wall for $\mathrm{St}^+ = 30$. We observe long streaks of particles (i.e. &amp;ldquo;ropes&amp;rdquo;) near the wall which remain stable for long periods of time.











  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/Vfp.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Top-down view of pseudocolor of fluid velocity overlayed by particle volume fraction near the wall for particles at $\mathrm{St}^+ = 30$. We observe the long ropes coinciding with the low-speed regions of the flow.











  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/lss.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Publications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dave, H. &amp;amp; Kasbaoui, M. H., Mechanisms of drag reduction by semi-dilute inertial particles in turbulent channel flow, Physical Review Fluids, 8, 084305 (08/21/2023).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Volume Filtered Immersed Boundary Method</title>
      <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/research_projects/ibm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davehimanshu.github.io/research_projects/ibm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Immersed Boundary Method (IBM) is a fully resolved approach towards multiphase flows originally proposed by Peskin (Flow patterns around heart valves: A numerical method in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Computational Physics&lt;/em&gt;, 1972) to study blood flow around heart valves. Later, Uhlmann (An immersed boundary method with direct forcing for the simulation of particulate flows in &lt;em&gt;Journal of Computational physics&lt;/em&gt;, 2005) presented a notable improvement over Peskins approach forcing the immersed boundary using a cloud of Lagrangian markers that define the surface of the solid. The forcing between the fluid Eulerian points and the solid surface Lagrangian points is coupled using interpolation and spreading techniques using the regularized Dirac delta. Many recent advances are based on Uhlmanns approach of the IBM formulation and show great improvement in the accuracy of the quantities calculated at the interface.&lt;/p&gt;


















&lt;figure  id=&#34;figure-a-description-of-the-ibm-approach-where-the-fluid-is-on-the-eulerian-grid-while-the-solid-surface-is-immersed-using-several-lagrangian-points&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A description of the IBM approach where the fluid is on the Eulerian grid while the solid surface is immersed using several Lagrangian points&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /media/ibm_1_hu23ee1196a3ab5afcfd6336d084041db9_171707_ef7f3d64d489cff3b48a159c245ecc63.webp 400w,
               /media/ibm_1_hu23ee1196a3ab5afcfd6336d084041db9_171707_a47ef38accf75afe213c6d0277a7a527.webp 760w,
               /media/ibm_1_hu23ee1196a3ab5afcfd6336d084041db9_171707_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/ibm_1_hu23ee1196a3ab5afcfd6336d084041db9_171707_ef7f3d64d489cff3b48a159c245ecc63.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;488&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure&amp;nbsp;&#34; data-post=&#34;:&amp;nbsp;&#34; class=&#34;numbered&#34;&gt;
      A description of the IBM approach where the fluid is on the Eulerian grid while the solid surface is immersed using several Lagrangian points
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach has recently gained significant traction with the increase in computational power recently due to its many benefits over conventional multiphase simulation approaches such as the body-fitted method. One of its most attractive features is the ability to allow for moving interfaces without the need for mesh regeneration, providing an significant increase in computational efficiency by saving time per step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While recent advances show significant improvement, certain questions still remain unanswered which stem from the ad-hocness of the methods:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the role of the internal flow within the immerses solid and how does it affect the quantities calculated at the interface?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the correct way to compute the Lagrangian marker volumes which arise during the computation of the forcing at the markers?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the accurate way to compute the hydrodynamic force at the interface?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We propose to answer these questions and attempt to properly formalize the forcing at the interface using the concept of volume filtering proposed by Anderson and Jackson (Fluid Mechanical Description of Fluidized Beds. Equations of Motion in &lt;em&gt;Industrial &amp;amp; Engineering Chemistry Fundamentals&lt;/em&gt;, 1967). This approach is similar in fashion to the Large-Eddy Simulation (LES) approach. The Navier-Stokes Equations are filtered with a filter kernal having a compact width of $\delta_f$. This produces the filtered Navier-Stokes Equations where the boundary conditions appear as right-hand-side terms involving surface integrals on the immersed boundary. Furthremore, sub-filter-scale terms arise similar in spirit to the LES equations which can be modeled, providing a path towards LES for immersed boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new Volume Filtered Immersed Boundary (VFIB) method is tested against various moving and static boundaries and shows excellent accuracy compared to previous IBM formulations, body-fitted approaches and experimental results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some examples of simulations using the VFIB approach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Laterally oscillating cylinder with cross flow at $Re_D = 185$: isocontours of positive (orange) and negative (green) vorticity are presented to show the wake behind the cylinder.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;











  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/oscillate.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Simulation of rotating blades on a drone to show the ability of the VFIB model to accomodate complex geometries: vorticity is displayed showing vortex structures in the wake of the blade.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;











  





&lt;video controls  &gt;
  &lt;source src=&#34;https://davehimanshu.github.io/media/quad.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34;&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Publications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dave, H., Herrmann, M. &amp;amp; Kasbaoui, M. H., The volume-filtering immersed boundary method, Journal of Computational Physics, 487, 112136 (08/15/2023).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://davehimanshu.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://davehimanshu.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
